<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lyle Klyne</title>
    <description>Design, development, documenting the process.</description>
    <link>http://lyleklyne.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://lyleklyne.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Design School</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Major update:&lt;/strong&gt; I will be attending the University of Washington this fall to pursue a &lt;a href=&quot;http://mhcid.washington.edu/&quot;&gt;Masters in Human-Computer Interaction and Design&lt;/a&gt;. The program is quite new, I will be a part of only the third cohort, but it draws curriculum from several well-established schools at UW. My classmates have quite diverse backgrounds, and I’m expecting to learn a great deal from students and faculty alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up until this point, I have taken the shotgun approach to learning. A smattering of books, blogs, online classes, learning from friends, trial and error, and trial by fire. I love learning this way and place a high value on being self-taught and proactive, but I know I thrive with a structured curriculum and a support network. For this reason, higher education is something I’ve been considering for a long time. After a lot of research I think this program will be an ideal next step, and I couldn’t be more excited!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other news, my friends over at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://facebook.com/foodisfree&quot;&gt;Food is Free Project&lt;/a&gt; began using a logo I designed for them. They open sourced the logo design to their social network last year, and I’m pleased to say that they will be using my design moving forward. I added the final design as well as my iterative process to my portfolio. Feel free to check it out &lt;a href=&quot;/portfolio/logo-food-is-free/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m working on several freelance jobs as well as some personal projects at the moment. My goal is to spend the summer honing programming and interactive prototyping chops to strengthen my toolbelt before entering graduate school. I’ve been learning &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pixate.com/&quot;&gt;Pixate&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.github.io/origami/&quot;&gt;Origami&lt;/a&gt; for prototyping; I’m taking an introductory Computer Science course, and creating a typeface as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More updates are coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 04:42:19 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lyleklyne.com/blog/design-school/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lyleklyne.com/blog/design-school/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Oh hey, world!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is long overdue.&lt;/strong&gt; For years, I have been making things, both digital and physical, and it’s time to make this process transparent. I’ve been reluctant to do so for some time. Partly because I’m hesitant to overshare, but also because it can be scary to put something you made out into the wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I believe the first is a legitimate concern, the later is not. From now on I will document my learning process here. I hope that this is personally beneficial and keeps me accountable, but I also hope it helps others in a similar position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This website will focus specifically on digital creation, placing special emphasis on usability design. I will illuminate my path towards designing and building digital products: the resources I use, the people I talk to, the struggles I encounter, as well as what I create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documenting this process will be two-fold. My portfolio will showcase design process as well as finished products, and my blog will focus on ideas, concepts, and resources. I will try to keep the tangential musings on adventure, philosophy and unrelated projects to a minimum, although some mention of these things will undoubtedly sneak in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like my kinesthetic approach to learning design and development, while writing this blog I will learn by doing. My initial goals are to establish some themes and recurring topics, as well as a schedule for posts. I feel like doing that last bit is especially important. &lt;strong&gt;In order to be successful in any occupation, you have to produce when you are burned out, uninspired, and ready to quit.&lt;/strong&gt; If anything I hope that this project urges me to do just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and please stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2015 07:31:19 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://lyleklyne.com/blog/oh-hey-world/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lyleklyne.com/blog/oh-hey-world/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
